# Patrick Aschermayr

Seeking a challenging and research-driven environment where I can make a meaningful contribution.

# Q London, United Kingdom p.aschermayr@gmail.com https://paschermayr.github.io https://github.com/paschermayr https://linkedin.com/in/patrickaschermayr https://twitter.com/PAschermayr

#### DOCTOR AL RESEARCH

# **Bayesian Inference on State Space Models**

My research area evolves around sequential parameter estimation and prediction for dependent latent variable models in a times series setting. In particular, I am working to improve the scalability of existing algorithms in terms of time and parameter size. This is particularly useful for financial and economic data, which often appear in a sequential setting.

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

University of Zurich & ZZ (Schweiz) AG **Portfolio Manager & Analyst** 

(FT) 2016 – 2018 Zurich, CH

I participated in a unique program where students manage parts of the university endowment. With three colleagues, I managed 2mn€ during my time in Switzerland. The focus of our Global Macro strategy was on Carry and Value, implemented via Bonds, Forwards, NDFs and Futures.

Deutsche Bank

(FT) 04/2016 - 07/2016 Frankfurt, GER

# Research - Strategic Beta Intern

I supported colleagues during the launch of Deutsche Asset model & strategy portfolios and implemented internal analysis tools, such as an order tool or performance & factsheets for mandates.

Case study: Breaking Expectations in a Diminishing Return Environment

Deutsche Asset Management

(FT) 10/2015 - 03/2016 Frankfurt, GER

# Portfolio Management - Multi Asset Intern

I implemented internal analysis tools, such as an index forecasting tool, sector update & a new issue sheet and supported PMs in daily tasks. *Case study: Hedging Convertible Bond Portfolios* 

# **PROJECTS**

(09/2020 - I2/2020) FINISHED

#### State Space Models Everywhere

A blog series on my website introducing hidden Markov and semi-Markov models in more detail. Later on, I build a Particle MCMC algorithm from scratch to estimate parameter from said models.

(08/2019 - ) ONGOING

# A Julia Library for State Space Model Inference

A (hopefully soon-to-be) open sourced Julia library for applying state of the art Bayesian inference algorithms for various state space models. A unique trait here is the ability to sequentially estimate parameter predict over time.

# **EDUCATION**

2018 - **Doctor of Philosophy** 

LONDON, UK Statistics

London School of Economics and Political Science

FULLY FUNDED BY THE ESRC

2016 – 2018 Master of Science

zurich, ch Quantitative Finance

ETH Zurich, University of Zurich

GPA: 5.4 (BEST:6.0)

2012 - 2015 **Bachelor of Science** 

VIENNA, AUT Economics, Business and Social Sciences

Vienna University of Economics and Business

GPA: 1.3 (BEST:1.0)

#### **REFERENCES**

References available on request

#### **CORE SKILLS**

STATISTICS/ML Bayesian Inference, particularly:

(Non-parametric) parameter estimation

Prediction

ALGORITHMS Markov Chain Monte Carlo

Sequential Monte Carlo

Filtering

COMPUTING Julia, Python, R

₽ŢX, Git

SOFT SKILLS Critical Thinking

Communication (Teaching and Blogging)

Adaptability

FINANCE KNOWLEDGE Basic Global Macro

Basic Factor Investing

Backtesting

#### **MISCELLANEOUS**

LANGUAGES German (Native), English (Fluent)

INVOLVEMENT LSE PhD student representative

Zurich QFin Alumni club

Local tennis and table football club

INTERESTS Books (fantasy, manga)

Sports (football, fitness) Cooking (Austrian, Asian) Gaming (Pokemon)

# **PUBLICATIONS**

# Articles in Peer-Reviewed Journals

Articles under Review

**Working Papers** 

**Book Chapters** 

#### **Conferences and Presentations**

05/2019 I presented my Particle MCMC poster at the Social and Economic Data Science Summit in London, UK.

#### **Invited Talks**

First author publications in **bold** 

#### **GRANTS AND AWARDS**

# **Awards and Honors**

# **Grants and Fellowships**

2018 – 2021 Economic and Social Research Council (ESRC) studentship

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

#### **London School of Economics**

Bayesian Inference - Teaching assistant, third year Bachelor level
Quantitative Methods - Teaching assistant, first year Bachelor level

#### **SER VICE**

# Journal Peer Review

# PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS

#### **CONSULTING ENGAGEMENTS**